# **Anton Shirikov**

Ph.D. Candidate, University of Wisconsin-Madison 110 North Hall, 1050 Bascom Mall, Madison, WI, 53706

🖂 shirikov@wisc.edu 🗘 shirikov 😵 shirikov.com | Updated: Oct. 16, 2021

I am a political scientist working on media, misinformation, polarization, and trust. I also study authoritarianism and elites and institutions in post-communist countries. My research relies on surveys, experiments, network analysis, and other quantitative methods.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Wisconsin–Madison, Ph.D. Candidate in Political Science

Expected Spring 2022

Dissertation: Who Trusts Untrustworthy Media? Political Biases and Information Credibility in Authoritarian Regimes

My dissertation examines why authoritarian state-run media are popular and trusted, despite their strong pro-government bias and the availability of other, unbiased, news sources. I combine original experiments and surveys situated in Russia with cross-national survey data to show that government supporters find propagandistic media credible, as such media reaffirm their beliefs. My analysis shows that political biases can undermine citizens' ability to recognize propaganda falsehoods and erode the power of alternative information sources. It also illuminates the limits of propaganda, which, as I show, is unlikely to appeal to oppositionminded citizens.

University of Wisconsin-Madison, M.A. in Political Science

2016

Moscow State Institute of International Relations, Candidate of Sciences in Political Science

2007

European University at St. Petersburg, M.A. in Political Science

2005

#### **WORKING PAPERS**

"Who Trusts State-Run Media? Polarized Perceptions of News Credibility in Non-Democracies" Under review

"Fake News for All: Misinformation and Polarization in Authoritarian Regimes" Under review

"Is Trust in Media Decreasing? Evidence from the World Values Survey"

"A Model of Censorship, Propaganda, and Repression" (with Scott Gehlbach, Zhaotian Luo, and Dmitriy Vorobyev)

"Smart Ways to Use a Postcommunist Dummy" (with Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera)

## **PUBLICATIONS**

**PAPERS** 

Forthcoming. "The Oligarch Vanishes: Defensive Ownership, Property Rights, and Political Connections." Quarterly Journal of Political Science. With John Earle, Scott Gehlbach, and Solomiya Shpak.

2021. "Who Gets Ahead in Authoritarian Parliaments? The Case of the Russian State Duma." The Journal of Legislative Studies.

2020. "Eurasia and Post-Communism: Weasel Words?" East European Politics and Societies & Cultures, Vol.34, No.2. With Yoshiko M. Herrera and Dmitrii Kofanov.

#### **BOOKS AND BOOK CHAPTERS**

Forthcoming. "Russia: Muddling Through Populism and the Pandemic." In: Renno, Lucio, and Nils Ringe (eds.). *Populists and the Pandemic: How Populists Around the World Respond to COVID-19*. Routledge. With Yoshiko M. Herrera and Valeriia Umanets.

2018. "Sovereignty and Regionalism in Eurasia." In: Paasi, Anssi, John Harrison, and Martin Jones (eds.). *Elgar Handbook on the Geographies of Regions and Territories*. Edward Elgar Publishing. With Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera.

2013. "Public Administration in Russia." In: Liebert, Saltanat, Stephen E. Condrey, and Dmitry Goncharov (eds.). *Public Administration in Post-Communist Countries: Former Soviet Union, Central and Eastern Europe, and Mongolia*. Routledge. With Dmitry Goncharov.

2010. Anatomiya Bezdeistviya. Politicheskiye Instituty i Konflikty v Budgetnom Processe Regionov Rossii [The Anatomy of Inaction. Political Institutions and Conflicts in the Budget Process of Russia's Regions] (in Russian). Saint-Petersburg: EUSP Press.

## **CONFERENCES**

APSA Annual Meeting (2020, 2021); MPSA Annual Conference (2018, 2019, 2021); ASEES Annual Convention (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020); NYU-CESS Conference (2021); Political Economy in a Changing World (HSE, Moscow, 2021); Wisconsin Russia Project Young Scholars Conference (2018, 2021); Communication Crossroads (UW–Madison, 2020); Studying Russia and the Postcommunist World (Columbia University, 2019); Regime Evolution, Institutional Change, and Social Transformation in Russia: Lessons for Political Science (Yale University, 2018); The Annual Meeting of the Society for Political Methodology (2017)

## **INVITED TALKS**

Populism and the Pandemic lecture series (UW–Madison, 2021); Kyiv School of Economics (2020)

#### OTHER PUBLIC TALKS

"Who Believes Propaganda? Media and Politics in Russia" (A lecture for the Participatory Learning and Teaching Organization at the Division of Continuing Studies at UW–Madison) 2020

"Russia's Strategies in Foreign Elections: What Does the Kremlin Want?" (A workshop for Wisconsin educators)

# **GRANTS AND AWARDS**

Facebook Foundational Integrity and Impact Research Grant (\$50,000, with Yoshiko Herrera, Mingcong Pan, and Yiming Wang). Project: "Understanding the Effects of Digital Restrictions on Affective Polarization"

Summer Dissertation Scholarship from the Department of Political Science at UW–Madison 2021 ASEES Summer Dissertation Writing Grant (\$6,000)

Summer Initiative Award from the Department of Political Science at UW–Madison 2021, 2020, 2019, 2017, 2016

Graduate student research award from the Center for Russia, East Europe, and Central Asia at UW–Madison (\$4,000)

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$16,000; joint with Georgiy Syunyaev). Project: "Learning about Bias: An Experiment on News Consumption in Russia"

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$10,245). Project: "Perceptions of Media Credibility in Non-Democracies: Evidence from Russia"

University Fellowship, UW-Madison

2015-2016, 2019-2020

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant for Yoshiko Herrera (UW-Madison)

Research Assistant for Kathryn Hendley (UW-Madison)

Spring and Summer 2021

Research Assistant for Nadav Shelef (UW-Madison)

Summer 2020

Research Assistant for Scott Gehlbach (UW–Madison) 2016-2018

# **TEACHING**

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Instructor, **Math Camp** for incoming graduate students in political science 2021, 2020, 2019
Teaching assistant, **PS170: Research Methods in Political Science** (Prof. Jessica Weeks) 2020, 2018
Lab instructor, **PS919: Intro to Machine Learning** (Prof. Adeline Lo) 2020

Teaching assistant, **PS120: Politics Around the World** (Prof. Nils Ringe)

#### **SERVICE**

Peer reviews of manuscripts for American Journal of Political Science, Post-Soviet Affairs, Problems of Post-Communism, East European Politics

Co-organizer of the **Comparative Politics Working Group** for graduate students (UW–Madison) 2019-present

Graduate student coordinator for the **Comparative Politics Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019 Graduate student coordinator for the **Political Economy Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019

# PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

American Political Science Association; Midwest Political Science Association; Association for Slavic, East European, and Eurasian Studies (ASEEES)

## **SOFTWARE**

R, Python, Stata, SQL, LaTeX, RMarkdown, HTML, Shiny, Git, Qualtrics

# **OTHER EXPERIENCE**

I have extensive experience of working as a journalist and editor in Russian independent media. For several years, I have served as deputy editor-in-chief and editor-in-chief at Slon.ru, and as opinions editor at the RBC news agency. I have also worked as editor at McKinsey & Company (all in Moscow, Russia).

# **REFERENCES**

Yoshiko M. Herrera, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin–Madison, yherrera@wisc.edu

Scott Gehlbach, Department of Political Science and Harris School of Public Policy, University of Chicago, gehlbach@uchicago.edu

Rikhil R. Bhavnani, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin–Madison, bhavnani@wisc.edu